<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Teratologia: or, a discovery of Gods vvonders, manifested in former and modern times by bloudy raine, and vvaters: vvith other prodigious occurences, being intimations of the divine displeasure; but withall, most gracious invitations to repentance. With certaine uses that a wise Christian will, and every Christian ought to make thereof. / By J. S.</title>
            <author>J. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94270</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S94</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E612_16</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206493</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865641</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865641</idno>
            <idno type="VID">165729</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94270)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165729)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 94:E612[16])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Teratologia: or, a discovery of Gods vvonders, manifested in former and modern times by bloudy raine, and vvaters: vvith other prodigious occurences, being intimations of the divine displeasure; but withall, most gracious invitations to repentance. With certaine uses that a wise Christian will, and every Christian ought to make thereof. / By J. S.</title>
                  <author>J. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 21, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Nath: Brooks at the Angell in Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "7ber 14th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Warnings --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>God --  Wrath --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:165729:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>TERATOLOGIA:</hi> OR, A DISCOVERY OF GODS VVONDERS, Manifeſted in former and modern times by Bloudy Raine, and VVaters: VVith other prodigious Occurrences, being intimations of the Divine Diſpleaſure; but withall, moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Invitations to REPENTANCE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With certaine <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes that a wiſe Chriſtian will, and every Chriſtian ought to make thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>J. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Fluunt multa ignaris mortalibus, occultis quibuſdum rerum cauſis &amp; mala, bona<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> agentibus aſtris nobis ſaepenumerò patent, ſed dum obſervare piget, omnia caſum facimus, neque prudentiae miniſterio &amp; induſtriâ conſiliorum, vel propenſa nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina invitamus vel minantis rabiem poti excludimus.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Marin. Bartetius, de vita &amp; geſt. Scanderbegi, l. 9. fol. 163.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed for <hi>Nath: Brooks</hi> at the Angell in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> 1650.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:165729:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:165729:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F my memory fail me not, I have read, but ſure I am, I have credibly heard, of a certain Creature that lives upon the water (ſo fooliſhly ſuttle) that upon the apprehenſion of any approaching danger, for ſecurity haſtens away, and hides its head in an hole; thinking, belike, thereby, that all is ſafe, when the head cannot be ſeen.</p>
            <p>How neer this comes in parallel to the nature of too many men will be acknowledged, when we conſider how indulgently favourable fleſh and bloud lookes upon it ſelf in its own way of naturall contentment and peace (<hi>awake not my Beloved,</hi> ſay they) how apt the moſt are to miſconſtrue judgments; and for a continuation of a being that the fleſh would have, and God will not; to make a fair gloſſe upon a bad Text, and to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret Gods meaning (deceiving their own ſoules) as themſelves would have it. The Jewes had a Cuſtome (which yet is, I am ſure lately was in uſe amongst them) to charme away noxious ſpirits, Hags or Night walkers from their Childrens cradles. Their Charm was, and is this, <hi>Adam, Eva, Hutz, Lilith:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Elias Levit. in Thiſt. Munſteri Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum.</note> 
               <hi>Adam, Eve,</hi> away Hag, out of doores Hob-gobling. And the Ancient Romans had their <hi>Lulla abi, Lulla abi,</hi> a ſong their Nurſes uſed at the Cradle to the very ſame purpoſe, as I have read. Now as ſuch a cuſtome was amongst them, ſo, is it not true that the condition of moſt of the ſons of Men is to ſing <hi>a requiem,</hi> or <hi>Lulla abi</hi> to their ſouls, to rock themſelves aſleep in the Cradle of ſecurity; and what in them lies to drive away
<pb facs="tcp:165729:3"/>all objects, ocular and mentall, (and to charme them as the Jewes did their <hi>Lilith,</hi> and the Romans their <hi>Lulla</hi>) and may contribute any thing to an interruption of the free fruition and enjoyment of fleſhly pleaſure and delight? whatſoever op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth, that is an enemy certainly; away with it therefore, out of dores with it in any caſe. By this meanes we plainly ſhun the wayes of God,<note place="margin">Jon. 1.</note> and <hi>Jonas</hi>-like, endeavour to flie (if ſuch a thing could be poſsible) from his preſence: And if he cannot be found reſident with us in our Earthly and Carnall contentments, in our luxury, covetouſneſſe, pride, and exceſſe, we care not (could his preſence be avoyded) to ſee him at all. God will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear unto men as it pleaſeth himſelfe, and according as they pleaſe, or diſpleaſe him, (there is no enchauntment hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon the <hi>Almighty,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Numb. 23.23.</note> to turn him this way, or that way, the breadth of an haire) if they doe well they ſhall be accepted; if otherwiſe,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.7.</note> 
               <hi>ſin,</hi> that is, puniſhment for ſin, <hi>lies at the dore.</hi> Sometimes we ſee him in his mercies, lets labour ever to keep him there; ſometimes we finde him in puniſhments, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in ſeeming, ſometimes in apparent judgements. Let it be our care upon all opportunities offered, to fall in, and cloſe with God by Humiliation, by Repentance, by Prayer, which will (being ſerious, fervent, and unfeigned) even bind the hands of the Almighty.<note place="margin">Exod. 32.10.</note> 
               <hi>Let me alone</hi> (ſaid God to <hi>Moſes</hi>) as if God had been diſabled from doing any thing till <hi>Moſes</hi> had left off praying. But alas! ſuch is our great folly, that which is, and ſhould be to us an occaſion of goodis, with a great many, even <hi>ſummâ induſtria,</hi> with the ſtrongeſt and higheſt bent of reluctancy declined, or with much contempt ('tis a ſad story to tell) pretermitted. What a ſtrange thing it is, that the very name, or word Hell, or a Book carrying that Title ſhould become ſo terrible, and ſhould force ſuch a melancholy impreſsion upon the ſoul, that it ſhould make both ſeller and buyer afraid to deal upon ſuch a ſubject! But I demand, is this well? Is that Soul
<pb facs="tcp:165729:3"/>in a good condition and ſtate thus affected and diſpoſed? I judg no man, it may be ſo, but 'tis two to one againſt it. It is a ſaying that the wiſe <hi>Exccleſiaſtes</hi> hath.<note place="margin">Eccles. 7.1, 2, 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>It is better</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to goe to the houſe of mourning, then to the houſe of feaſting, &amp;c.</hi> And againe, <hi>ſorrow is better then laughter, for by the ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the countenance the heart is made better. The heart of the wiſe is in the houſe of mourning, but the heart of fooles is in the houſe of mirth.</hi> Will we know the way to Heaven? it is <hi>through the Valley of Baca,</hi> weeping in a dry,<note place="margin">Pſal. 84.6.</note> barren, troubleſome, and unpleaſant paſſage, where there is no refreſhing ſpring to be found, but what by digging, and hard labour, we work out of the fountains of Divine Conſolation, the Scriptures, which open their breaſts unto us, from whence we may ſeek ſuch nouriſhment as will feed our ſoules to eternall life. Along this valley, the Valley of Affliction, you ſhall trace the pious Votaries, and find the holieſt of Gods Saints of Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent times in their pilgrimage towards Heaven.<note place="margin">Heb. 11.25.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> choſe rather <hi>to ſuffer affliction with the People of God, then to enjoy the pleaſures of ſinne for a ſeaſon.</hi> How heartily and cheerfully did that Holy man, <hi>Ignatius,</hi> (condemned to be torne in pieces by the teeth of Beaſts) break forth, and ſay,<note place="margin">Euſeb. Eccl. Hiſt. l. 3. c. 36. ex Irenaei. l. 5. adverſus Haereſes.</note> 
               <hi>Frumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ego ſum Dei, &amp;c. I am</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Gods Corne, and am ground and kneaded with the teeth of beaſts, that I may be made clean or white bread for Chriſt.</hi> O bleſſed magnanimity, and higheſt example of Chriſtian fortitude!<note place="margin">Ignes, cruces, beſtiae diſperſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones oſſium, diſcerptioneſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> membrorum, ac totius cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris poenae &amp; omnia in me unum ſupplicia Diaboli arte quaeſita cumulentur, dummodo Jeſum Chriſtum merear adipiſci. <hi>Euſeb. ubi ſupra.</hi> Heb. 1.2.6, 7, 8. Pſal. 94.12.</note> This, this is the way to Heaven, which to all is not given to walk in, nor hath God required it, but onely from ſuch as he hath enabled to undergoe ſo ſharpe a paſſage: no one of Gods Children is without his <hi>ſcourge,</hi> his <hi>chaſtiſement,</hi> of one ſort or another, <hi>and bleſſed is he whom the Lord chaſtneth,</hi> he receives none but ſuch. But enough for a Preface, (a large
<pb facs="tcp:165729:4"/>gate, or entrance, into a ſmall Building) <hi>Cavenda ſuperna vulnera,</hi> that followes, <hi>Wounds on high, or from above</hi> (the ſubject of the conſequent work) <hi>are to be taken heed of.</hi> For, as ſure as we live, if we ſmite God by our ſinnes, we ſhall be againe ſmitten by his puniſhments, wound for wound, blow for blow, is Gods impartiall Talio. What ever we doe, then lets be eſpecially heedfull that we fall not into the <hi>reveng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> hands of God;<note place="margin">Heb. 10.31. Pſal. 2.12.</note> for if his <hi>wrath be kindled,</hi> yea, <hi>but a little, bleſſed are all they that put their truſt in him.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:165729:4"/>
            <head>TERATOLOGIA. <hi>OR,</hi> A diſcovery of Gods Wonders manifeſted in former and moderne times by Bloudy Raine and Waters, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>LOUD, when ever it hath been ſeen to fall from the Skies, or Clouds, in the nature of Raine, or flowing out of the earth in the manner of a Fountaine, hath alwayes occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned matter of great fear to the behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; and hath oftentimes been the fore-runners of deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to Cities and Countries where it hath appeared, or God hath otherwiſe diſpoſed and appointed it. So merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full is the God of mercy, that before he ſtrike, he will give warning. When precept upon precept, line upon line, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction upon inſtruction, admonition upon admonition,<note place="margin">Iſay 28.10.</note> will not prevail to call in obſtinate perſons to obedience: when there is no remedy,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 36.16.</note> then God preſents his Rod by viſible and prodigious tokens of his enſuing wrath; as Plague and Peſtilence, Famine and War, (a Catalogue of them we find in <hi>Leviticus</hi>) by ſignes in the Sun and Moon,<note place="margin">Lev. 26.</note> by fearfull ſights, and lights not uſuall in the Skies: By Blazing Stars and Comets, by Earthquakes, by flowing and raining of Bloud, and falling downe of Iron, with what elſe he is pleaſed to make uſe of to give a demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his diſpleaſure. Now that which I deſire briefly to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:165729:5"/>do upon this ſubject is this, namely, to make a ſhort relation of ſome prodigious apparitions, which in former times have preſented themſelves to beholders, from, and out of the Aire, but more eſpecially of that ſtrange kind of flowing and raining of Bloud, and falling down of Iron. And to this end, firſt, to let ſuch men know, that know it not, that the ſame things, to wit, the raining of Bloud, &amp;c. have been in former times as they have fallen out in the latter. A few inſtances of many moe I could produce out of <hi>Lycoſthenes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lychoſthen. de prodigiis &amp; oftent.</note> and others I have ſet down in the enſuing diſcourſe. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, upon the conſideration of ſuch portentous appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritions to draw out inſtructions for learning, and informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the unlearned, and ſimpler ſort. To proceed then.</p>
            <p>In the year of the world 3729. In <hi>Italie,</hi> in a Town there now called <hi>Marca Ancona,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Funccius ex Eutropio. Garcaeus in Meteorolog. 477.</note> the ſeat of the Ancient Picen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, inhabitants of <hi>Picenum,</hi> a River there flowed with Bloud. And at <hi>Toſcana,</hi> formerly called <hi>Tuſcia,</hi> the ſame year the Heavens ſeemed to be on Fire, and three Moones were ſeen at <hi>Ariminum,</hi> now called <hi>Rimine.</hi> In the year alſo 3783. in <hi>Rome,</hi> in a place there called <hi>Area Concordia,</hi> it rained Bloud for two dayes together as <hi>Livy</hi> hath decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red;<note place="margin">Liv. dec. 4. l. 9. p. 624.</note> and ſo in like manner it did in <hi>Area Vulcani</hi> a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that time, as the ſame <hi>Livy</hi> doth report, <hi>Decad.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 610. which brought the people out of fear of enſuing danger to ſupplicate their Gods by a ſolemne appointment or proclamation, <hi>Ejus prodigii expiandi cauſâ:</hi> and to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie their indignation by ſacrifices, or ſuch manner of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh ſervice as then was uſed amongſt them.<note place="margin">Plin. H. Nat. l. 2. c. 56.</note> 
               <hi>Pliny</hi> tells us, that in the year when <hi>Marcus Acitius,</hi> and <hi>Caius Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> were Conſuls, it rained Bloud and Milk, about the year of the World 3852. and alſo ſaith, that a Light from Heaven was ſeen, <hi>C. Coecilius,</hi> and <hi>C. Papyrius</hi> bing Conſuls
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:165729:5"/>the next year after in the night time ſo bright, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t diei ſpecies noctu luceret,</hi> that it ſhined, or was light as the day. The ſame <hi>Pliny</hi> alſo writes, that amongſt the <hi>Lucani,</hi> a people of <hi>Italy,</hi> whoſe Country is now called <hi>Baſilicata,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plin.</note> Iron in the forme of ſpunges fell down from above, the year before <hi>Marcus Craſſus</hi> was ſlaine of the <hi>Parthians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Funccius.</note> being about the year of the world <hi>3910.</hi> at which time a great abundance of Souldiers that he brought along with him out of <hi>Leu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caine</hi> were cut off, and their lives loſt in that fight with the <hi>Parthians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to paſſe by the Stories of more Ancient times, and to come ſomewhat lower towards the preſent times. In the year of Chriſt, or neer about 856. in the time of <hi>Lewis</hi> the firſt, at <hi>Brixia,</hi> a City of <hi>Lumbardy,</hi> in rained Bloud three dayes and nights, as <hi>Naucler</hi> reports; and ſo it did,<note place="margin">Naucler. Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerat. 29. pag. 713.</note> but not for ſo long a time, amongſt the <hi>Franks,</hi> in the year <hi>879.</hi> as is read in <hi>Speculum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In, or about the year of Chriſt 935. at <hi>Genua,</hi> a City in <hi>Italy,</hi> a f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>taine of Bloud was there ſeen to flow; and the City was that ſame year ranſackt by the <hi>Sarazens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem. Gen. 32. p. 728.</note> and all put to the Sword, beſides women and Children, as <hi>Nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cler</hi> tells us. And the ſame <hi>Naucler</hi> doth alſo report, that in <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1104. Bloud was ſeen to flow from Bread at <hi>Spira: Bellum Civile ſignificans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem. Gen. 37. p. 801.</note> 
               <hi>ſignifying</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill War like to enſue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the dayes of <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, and about the year of Chriſt <hi>1180.</hi> it rained Bloud in <hi>England,</hi> in what part cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly of the Land mine Author declares not: which the people apprehending to be a prodigious thing, and being thereat moved, began to ſuſpect the Government of <hi>John,</hi> whereof they were afraid, as <hi>Polydor Virgil</hi> notes.<note place="margin">Hiſt. Angl. l. 13. p. 236.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In a Town or Village called <hi>Mirkalow,</hi> between the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of <hi>Odera</hi> and <hi>Niſſa</hi> in <hi>Sileſia,</hi> it rained Bloud three
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:165729:6"/>dayes together about the year 1269.<note place="margin">Crom. Hiſt. Polon. l. 9. p. 162,</note> as <hi>Cromerus</hi> hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</p>
            <p>In the year 1274. in the time of <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt, after an Earthquake that ſpoiled and threw down many beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Buildings in <hi>Wales,</hi> Bloud was there alſo ſeen to fall like raine from the Heavens,<note place="margin">Polydor. Virgil l. 17. H. Anglic ſtatim ab ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio.</note> 
               <hi>Quaſi prodigium exitiale illi genti cujus ſanguine brevi tempore poſtea ea regio paſsim maduit: As a fatall prodegie</hi> (ſaith <hi>Polydor Virgil</hi>) <hi>to that Nation, with whoſe Bloud a ſhort time after that Country was all over moiſtned, or made wet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the ſame <hi>Polydor</hi> alſo writes, that <hi>Will: Rufus</hi> taking a Journey into <hi>Normandy</hi> to acquaint himſelf with the ſtate of his Affairs there, a Fountain near <hi>Abington</hi> was ſeen to flow with Bloud three dayes together after his departure hence,<note place="margin">Idem l. 10. p. 176.</note> and the Heavens ſeemed to be on fire. And what followed? <hi>Polydor</hi> ſaith, that this King going over, made but ſhort ſtay there; and returning into <hi>England,</hi> was ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned back again by a report that <hi>Conſtantes,</hi> a famous old City in <hi>Normandy,</hi> was beſieged by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>nch. To which place the King made his addreſſe with all poſſible ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition; and taking with him but a few, came on with ſuch ſpeed and reſolution, that the beſiegers affrighted, made all the haſte they could to be gone, but over taken by pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite, there were ſlaughtered to a very great number; This was about the year of Chriſt 1464.</p>
            <p>To be brief, for there be already noted examples enough. In <hi>Kalenburg</hi> Caſtle,<note place="margin">Crantz. Saxon. l. 12. c. 5.</note> ſaith <hi>Crantzius,</hi> and about the ſame year 1464. it rained Bloud; <hi>for the drops thereof were ſeen</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>upon womens vails, and upon ſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that lay near this Caſtle.</hi> And he ſaith further, that a little after this rain, the ſun was there ſeen at noon, <hi>ſine ſplendore, without ſplendor or brightneſſe; And this followed</hi> (ſaith <hi>Crantzius</hi>) <hi>Warres were exaſperated, Inter Duces, &amp; Civitates Saxionae, between the Dukes and Cities of</hi> Saxonie.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:165729:6"/>
            <p>Laſtly, and of late times in <hi>Gloceſter-ſhire</hi> at a Village called <hi>Barnwood,</hi> (upon the report of the neighbourhood who beheld it, I have no other knowledge of this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar) in the moneth of <hi>February,</hi> 1648. it rained Bloud upon certaine Clothes waſhed, and hung upon an Hedg there to dry: Many eyes beheld it, but what the conſequence may be is ſecret hidden in the boſome of the great, and Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcient God, whoſe judgements are <hi>unſearchable,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 11.13.</note> 
               <hi>and his wayes paſt finding out.</hi> Let no man preſume to draw neer, or attempt to open the Cabinet of theſe Divine Counſells, that are only reſerved to himſelfe. And now to haſten for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. <hi>Pliny</hi> tells us in the place above mentioned, where he ſpeaks of Bloudy raine, but eſpecially of Iron that fell from the Heavens in the forme of ſpunges, that the Sooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers being conſulted, and enquired of, what the ſame might portend, anſwered,<note place="margin">Plin. vide ſupra.</note> 
               <hi>Cavenda praemonuerunt ſuperna vulnera: The ſame did forewarn</hi> (ſaid they) <hi>that ſupernall wounds were to be taken heed of.</hi> Loe, theſe are ſtrange things, even wonders in our eyes: Let's therefore leave them to God, the Author of them, and endeavour to make ſome good uſe of them, to the benefit and good of our ſoules. And what ſhall that be?</p>
            <p>Why, even this. Let it ſerve in the firſt place to exhort every wiſe Chriſtian, not to put far away the <hi>evil day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 6.3.</note> build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon a vaine confidence, and flattering themſelves with fallacious hopes, and groundleſſe collections, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing peace to themſelves when the judgements of God are even at their dores. This was the fault of the <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> his time, and the ſame was the fault of them both in the Prophet <hi>Iſaiahs</hi> time,<note place="margin">Iſay 22.12.</note> (who propheſied about fifty years before <hi>Amos</hi>) and whereof he complains, ſaying, <hi>When the Lord God of Hoſts in that time calleth to weeping, to mourning, and to baldneſſe, and to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:165729:7"/>girding with ſackcloth, behold joy and gladneſſe, &amp;c.</hi> Much adoe the Lord had with theſe untoward people. <hi>Hegeſippus</hi> writes,<note place="margin">Hegeſip. de ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cid. Urbis Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſol. l. 5. c. 44.</note> that, though they had a great many of warnings by prodigious ſignes, and fearfull apparitions before <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> was beſieged, and the City deſtroyed; yet the moſt of them had a way of expounding the meaning of thoſe appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritions in a better ſenſe to themſelves then God intended them; putting away the Evill day, till the Vengeance of God fell upon the heads of them in a moſt ſevere manner, as they that will take the paines to peruſe <hi>Joſephus</hi> and <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſippus,</hi> Authors of note and credit, (both which have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that Story) will eaſily ſee.</p>
            <p>The next uſe will be a uſe of Admonition to all ſorts of people to be very heedfull of their wayes. When God ſpeaks let no man cloſe his ears, but ſay as <hi>Samuel</hi> once: <hi>Speak Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>for thy ſervant heareth.</hi> How well is the Lord pleaſed with a ready returne? how ſoone doth he receive thoſe that come unto him, and tenderly embrace any that tremble at his threats? Such a one let him aſſure himſelfe ſhall finde mercy when contemners ſhall not eſcape miſery and unhappineſſe. And to make us aſſured how ready he is to come in to our aſſiſtance, when we come in to call upon him for it, how willing to bear our infirmities, and to pardon our failings; to cure our wounds that ſinne hath made in our Soules, and to ſtir us forward not to be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to our ſelves:<note place="margin">John 4.24.</note> loe, he doth diſcover and manifeſt himſelfe <hi>(being a Spirit)</hi> under ſuch notions as are moſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractive to any nature, by all the parts and paſſions of man, by the neareſt relations that intercede in our common ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties, by all tenderneſſe of Paternall and maternall affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons he declares himſelfe. He hath (to ſuite with our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) a face, a mouth, he hath noſtrils, eyes, ears, armes, hands, &amp;c. he hears, he ſees, he ſmels, &amp;c. By all the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:165729:7"/>and internall ſenſes (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) affected in ſhew after the manner of a man, he makes himſelf known unto us, and doth declare, and demonſtrate with all tenderneſſe of affection, himſelf ready to aſſiſt at every need: Nay, how paſſionate he is in our ſufferings; he calls to be called upon.<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 50.15.</note> 
               <hi>Call upon me</hi> (me that am a<note n="†" place="margin">Quis ille no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus eſt Pater? Deus ſcil. tam Pater nemo, tam pius ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo. <hi>Tcrtul. de poenit. p.</hi> 45.</note> Father) <hi>in the time of trouble, and I will help thee, and thou ſhalt glorifie me.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 11.28.</note> 
               <hi>Come onto me</hi> (me that am a Saviour) <hi>all ye that labour and are heavy laden, and I will eaſe you.</hi> He ſues to be ſued, and ſought unto, and takes it as a courteſie done to him to aske a favour from him. He hath an heart, he hath bowels, bowels of compaſſion feeling under humane infirmities. He is <hi>grieved</hi> at our miſcarriage, he is glad at our well doing;<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.30.</note> there's joy in Heaven over one ſinner that repents, more then over ninety nine righteous perſons that need no repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Finally, what ever may conduce towards the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and drawing of a man to his owne Salvation, the Lord God of mercy imparts to him under ſuch repreſentatives as may cauſe him with boldneſſe, alacrity, and cheerfulneſſe, to be ſtill calling and craving for neceſſary ſupplies for Heaven, whilſt time and opportunity laſts, whereunto we have great and manifold encouragements. Chriſt Jeſus our elder brother, <hi>made in the ſhape of man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2.7.</note> is our Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, our Mediatour, our Interceſſor, our Judge, our Friend, our <hi>All in All.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 3.11.</note> Loſe not then to day what cannot (perhaps) be gain'd to morrow, we are not ſure of another<note n="*" place="margin">Omnem cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de diem tibi diluxiſſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premum. <hi>Horat.</hi>
               </note> day. Yet an opportunity tenders it ſelfe, and a Kingdome may be purchaſed at a low rate, and with a little labour. Let not this Kingdome now to be gotten with ſo ſmall adoe be loſt for not asking for, nor ſeeking after; we are commanded and taught by our Saviour, to <hi>ſeek it in the firſt place,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 6.33.</note> before all other things. But ſee how little of Heaven the moſt of us have in us, how little we value it, by this it is evident.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:165729:8"/>Who, amongſt us, all having a promiſe made him to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed as Heir to an Earthly Prince, in a poor Kingdom upon condition, ſo and ſo to lead his life, and to demeane him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to abſtaine from this and that diſorder, no way bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſome to nature; from fleſhly pleaſures, that after act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing are<note n="*" place="margin">Proba iſtas quae voluptates vocantur ubi tranſcenderint modum poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas eſſe. <hi>Senec. Ep.</hi> 83. <hi>p.</hi> 129.</note> 
               <hi>grievous,</hi> from carnall delights eaſily forborn; to do his uttermoſt endeavour to expreſſe readineſſe of ſervice, with a willing mind to ſo free a Donor, ſo bountifull a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactor: Who (I ſay) would not accept theſe conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon ſuch termes with all thankfulneſſe? But this Kingdome, the Kingdome of Heaven, being in all its pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges and prerogatives, ſo farre beyond all the dignities and prerogatives of an Earthly Kingdome, and ſo tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſurpaſſing all imaginable earthly felicities, is but ſlightly (I am afraid) and careleſly thought upon, and but by a few thought on at all. God open our eyes, and cauſe us at length to look about us. The time of our accompt is not farre off, when, certainly, no man knowes. Let's there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>redeem the time,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.16.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe the dayes are evill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A third uſe is to draw us to a ſerious conſideration, and to a diligent examination, what the cauſe is that ſo much bloud is emptied, and drawn out of the veines of this Land by a Civill Warre, that yet continues eſpecially amongſt our neighbours with ſo much bitterneſſe, and ſuch height of ſtomack and hoſtility. And what remedy muſt be ſought after, and with endeavour may be found to ſtop ſo bad an effect. For my part I ſhall declare the reſult of mine examination of this particular, which is briefly this. Sinne it is, that, and nothing but that, hath provoked Gods di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpleaſure. We have ſmitten God by the repetition of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny horrid tranſgreſſions, and high contempts, ſerved him with no better ſacrifice and devotion, than what hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from hearts as hard as Adamant, yea, iron hearts.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:165729:8"/>By which meanes he is offended; and as we have preſented him, ſo hath he let fall upon us Iron, with all materialls of Warre, and inſtruments of Vengeance to wound and plague us for our diſobedience and impenitency. We have walked <hi>contrary to God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lev. 26.25.</note> and therefore hath he brought the Sword upon us, which is drawn out, and cannot again be ſheathed, till he, he I ſay, that ſhuts up the Sea with dores as <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks, and ſaith, <hi>Hitherto ſhalt thou come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 38.8.</note> 
               <hi>and no farther, and here ſhall thy proud waves be ſtayed;</hi> and he that rebukes the winds, <hi>and they are ſtill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 8.26.</note> commands it to be re-inſheathed, which (upon turning to him, and amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, being the only remedy in this caſe to be made uſe of, and which he hath long expected fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> us, but yet not found as it ſhould be) he is quickly (ſee how quickly he is) able to doe it. <hi>O that my people had hearkned unto me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 81.13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>and Iſrael had walked in my wayes, I ſhould have ſoone</hi> (or <hi>how ſoone could I have</hi>) <hi>ſubdued their enemies, and turned mine hand againſt their adverſaries.</hi> Certainly, what to man ſeemes impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, is to him, who is<note n="*" place="margin">El Schaddai Gen. 17.1. Gen. 18.14.</note> All-ſufficient, and Allmighty, to whom nothing is too hard, moſt eaſie. At the only noiſe, or blaſt of Trumpets made of Rams Hornes, enforced by the divine breath which only is powerfull, and wonderfull, how ſoone did the wall of <hi>Jericho</hi> fall to the ground?<note place="margin">Joſh. 6.20.</note> There's no fortification can ſtand againſt the Almighty. God puts on <hi>Gideon</hi> to fight againſt the <hi>Amalekites</hi> and <hi>Midi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judges 7.</note> with all their multitudes, all the children of the Eaſt. <hi>Gideon</hi> was but 300 ſtrong, but the Enemy without number, as the ſands by the Sea ſide for multitude; ye he went on againſt this vaſt Army (ſo true it is, that elſwhere is ſpoken,<note place="margin">1 Sam. 14.6. 2 Chron. 14.11.</note> that there <hi>is no reſtraint to the Lord to ſave by many or few</hi>) with his handfull, and by the power of God, <hi>The Sword of the Lord and of Gideon</hi> (ſo went up the cry againſt the Enemy) and with their Trumpets, Pitchers, and Lamps
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:165729:9"/>(poor weapons a man would think) they ſubdued them all, yea themſelves (God having ſo ordained) ſubdued and killed one another to a very great number.<note place="margin">1 Sam. 17.50.</note> 
               <hi>Davids</hi> conqueſt of <hi>Goliah</hi> is not to be forgotten, nor what <hi>NaZianZen</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> have obſerved thereupon: His weapons were but mean <hi>(a ſling, a little ſtone)</hi> conſidering the ſtrength of this <hi>Philiſtian</hi> Gyant; yet ſo happily was this ſtone guided, and ſet forward, that it had ſoone found its mark, and done its work; for (ſaith the Text) <hi>Immerſo lapide in frontem ejus cecidit pronus in terram, the ſtone was drown'd, or ſunk into his forehead.</hi> But this ſtone went along with more then its own materialls.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Naz. in Julian. Orat. 2. p. 308. Chryſ. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> For <hi>NaZianZen</hi> tells us it was a Myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſtone, and <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> explaines the Myſtery, ſaying, <hi>That David overcame this Gyant not with weapon, or Sword, but Prayers.</hi> God is able to doe infinitely more then we can think or aske, if we be not wanting to our ſelves, he wants no power. The Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtory tells us that <hi>Eugenius</hi> an Uſurper (upon the death of <hi>Valentinian</hi> the Emperour, who was treacherouſly murthered, as 'tis thought, by one <hi>Argobaſtus</hi> a perfidious Captain in his Army) led on a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great power of Souldiery, accompanyed with this <hi>Argo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſtus</hi> to the Alpes,<note place="margin">Ruffin. Eccl. hiſt. l. 11. c. 33.</note> with an intention to invade <hi>Italy;</hi> and after the example of <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtat, to ſet up and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh Idolatry. Againſt this Tyrant <hi>Eugenius, Theodoſius</hi> the Emperour prepares, leads on an Army, which being much inferiour to the Enemies power, and he thereupon doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full what to doe; he falls to Prayer, receives an anſwer and warrant by a Viſion in the night to join Battail: which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly he did, and gave the <hi>Pagans</hi> ſuch a Charge, that ſoone made them turn their backs; the Wind, upon the ſuddaine, riſing in ſo violent a manner, that it forced back the Darts they caſt into their own faces. Hence it was that <hi>Claudian,</hi> a Chriſtian Poet, hath theſe Verſes.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:165729:9"/>
            </p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>O nimium dilecte Deo, cui militat aether,</l>
                  <l>Et conjurati veniunt ad claſsica venti.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Skie and Windes conjur'd for thee contend,</l>
                  <l>With Trumpets joyn'd, Gods much endeared friend.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>Was not that a ſtrange defeat and overthrow that <hi>Ula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſlaus,</hi> King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> received by <hi>Amurath</hi> the Turk? <hi>Amurath,</hi> and this <hi>Uladiſlaus,</hi> had Armies ready for the Field and Battail: Conditions of peace were tendered, and on both ſides received; Articles drawn and Sworn unto, by them and th'other party, the Chriſtian takes the Goſpel, and the Turk the Alcoran. The Turk hereupon drawes off, being confident of Chriſtian fidelity, and away he goes.<note place="margin">Bonfin. de reb. Ungar. l. 6. dec. 3. p. 462. &amp;c.</note> Being gone ſome few dayes Journey, the Army, under the Command of <hi>Uladiſlaus,</hi> by the perſwaſion of <hi>Julian</hi> the Popes Legat, break their Faith with the Turk, taking certain Townes contrary to the Agreement ſolemnly made and ſworne to. Whereof the Turk (though farre remote) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing given to underſtand, with all poſſible ſpeed returnes to <hi>Varna,</hi> in the confines of <hi>Myſia,</hi> neer to which place <hi>Ula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſlaus</hi> his Forces lay. Both Armies met againe, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any further diſpute fall on: A great ſlaughter was made on both ſides, but eſpecially in the Turkiſh, till <hi>Amurath,</hi> at the length, fearing the loſſe of the day, drew out of his Boſome, the Articles of true concluded upon between him and the Chriſtians, and lifting up his eyes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Heaven, with the writing in his hand, he thus brake forth: <hi>Haec ſunt (inquit ingeminans) Jeſu Chriſti foedera, &amp;c. Theſe, theſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>are the Convenants which thy Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans have made with me; by thy Divine power they have ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly Sworne, and violated their Faith given under thy Name, they have treacherouſly denyed their own God. Now
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:165729:10"/>O Chriſt, if thou be a God (as they ſay, and that we are in an Errour) revenge, I beſeech thee, here in this place, the wrongs done both to thee and me, and manifeſt to thoſe that as yet have not known thy holy name, the puniſhments due for breach of Faith.</hi> Theſe words were ſcarcely out of the Turks mouth, but preſently an alteration appeared in the Battail, downe went the Chriſtians (formerly ſucceſſefull and victorious) apace, and the King ſlaine, they fled with a very great loſſe, even the loſſe of many thouſands of their lives on the ſudden. O the incomparable wiſdome, impartiall juſtice, and irreſiſtable power of our God! See, his ears are open to an Infidell calling upon him for juſtice; he reſpects no mans perſon, but where evill is committed, puniſhment ſhall be repaid aſſuredly, and how ſoon he can doe it, he hath made ſufficiently known. Should I not be tedious to the Reader, I could tell him how God delivered from Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhment, and the Sword, the poor <hi>Rocheleers</hi> in the yeer 1573, and how quickly he did it, making them able (after that bloudy Maſſacre) to hold out againſt all the power of the <hi>French,</hi> that Beſieged, and endeavoured to ſtop all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion from them. And how did he bring it to paſſe? why, even thus:<note place="margin">De ſtatu reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionis in reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Galliae. <hi>Comment. fol.</hi> 106.</note> He ſent a certain kind of fiſh, never ſeen nor heard of before, (they called them Surdones) that every day pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented themſelves during the Siege near the ſhoar to be made uſe of. By which means the people being nouriſhed, untill they had made their conditions of peace with the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; and they removing, the Fiſhes alſo departed, that very ſame day, ſaith mine Author. Eighty eight we muſt all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member with thankfull hearts, what haſte God made to come in to the relief of his people; and the ſuddaine ceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the great Plague muſt never be forgotten, but muſt be acknowledged to be his alone work, ſo eaſie and ready is his eare to heare a Prayer, though weak, and to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:165729:10"/>take notice of but a very little humiliation; and how quickly he is able to bring to paſſe his own work, be it never ſo great we ſee. Let then this be our comfort, we have found God willing, and able to help at any need, let us make much of ſuch a friend whilſt he may be had, and by all means de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline that thing whatſoever it be, pleaſure, or profit, and ſhun it with deteſtation that may hazard the loſſe of him. And let us take notice by the way that there is no wound, no plague, hath ever fallen upon a people, from theſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme powers, but by occaſion of wounds firſt received. Which being ſo,</p>
            <p>Let us then in the next and laſt place goe on with a uſe of reproof, wherein I ſhall, and doe much blame ſuch perſons as let goe the reines to all kindes of licentiouſneſſe, and vicious living, taking no care to <hi>mortifie</hi> ſin in the fleſh,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.13.</note> but wholly to live after the fleſh; and as much as in them lieth, <hi>quenching the ſpirit;</hi> alſo <hi>Crucifying</hi> (as I may ſay) <hi>the Son of God afreſh,</hi> and wounding, at almoſt every word,<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.19. Heb. 6.6.</note> the Majeſty of the High God of Heaven and Earth, by their curſed, and never till of late heard of, helliſh Oaths and Imprecations. <hi>Bloud and Wounds</hi> are become complements in ordinary language and communication, paſſing off with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out paſſion, or any commotion or provocation inducing thereunto. And ſo common hath this wicked and moſt unchriſtian kind of ſpeaking been amongſt us, (thanks to the Parliament for their pious Act againſt it) that almoſt no notice at all hath been taken of it. Upon this too too common miſcarriage of men in theſe unhappy times, I ſhall make bold to re-aſſume, and repeat my precedent Theame, namely, <hi>Cavenda ſuperna vulnera: Heed, and great beed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed</hi> (there being very great cauſe) <hi>ſhould be taken, that the powers above be not wounded,</hi> namely, this way, <hi>by our care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, inconſiderate, and rebellious words and actions.</hi> If he ſhall
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:165729:11"/>not be guiltleſſe, (and God declares he ſhall not) that but only takes his name in Vain, that is, without due reverence: Oh then what ſhall become of him that ſtudies to find out new Oathes to blaſpheme and diſhonour his Name? If for <hi>every idle word</hi> that a man ſpeaks,<note place="margin">Mat. 12.36.</note> an accompt will be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted at the laſt day, as our Saviour hath foretold us. Oh then let the preſumptuous and profane Swearer lay this to heart, and know, that without timely repentance, ſad and fearfull will be the account that he muſt give at that Great, and to the Wicked, that moſt terrible appearance: If, laſtly, one erring thought, be of that dangerous conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence that puts a man to the hazard of his ſalvation, as S. <hi>Peter</hi> in that caſe of <hi>Simon Magus</hi> doth ſeeme to imply, and which,<note place="margin">Act. 8.22.</note> to ſubdue, and to bring into Captivity to the obedience of Chriſt,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 10.5.</note> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, was a part of his ſpirituall task, or warfare; What then may ſuch a one ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, that all his life long doth cheriſh evill thoughts with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out controll, giving way and conſent to their operation, the product whereof, is nothing but blaſphemy and horrible tranſgreſſion? 'Tis to me indeed, a wonder to hear ſo many men that came to the Church, ſort themſelves as good Chriſtians amongſt the Congregation, hear the Word of God preached, and partake of the Ordinances, and the means appointed for every mans convoy and direction to eternall happineſſe: Yet in their common converſe and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, doe make no conſcience at all of an Oath; nay, of many, and many oaths; and thoſe of an high nature too, as big as they can ſpeak them, and take no long time about it, but even as faſt as the tongue will walk. Oaths flie out intermixed in every paſſage and occaſion without ſenſe or feeling. What ſhall we think of theſe men? For my part, I think, truly thus, That ſuch men fear not God, but plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contemne him. Nature it is not that makes a man a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:165729:11"/>Swearer, it forceth not, it inticeth not to ſuch exorbitancy: But 'tis a vicious cuſtome aſſumed, received by the care, and entertained (in the abſence of grace) by the affections, and ſo continued, it hardens, and by degrees doth cauterize the Conſcience in ſuch manner, that at length it becomes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void of ſence; and ſuch a perſon, (as I have heard of many) reprehended for ſwearing, will ſwear that he did not ſwear. Now this tranſgreſſion foſtered and entertained to ſuch a growth, hath many times been ſeen to flie out upon provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations and diſtemperatures (eſpecially when drink hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed, or loſſes or croſſes in gaming, or otherwiſe have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperated) ſo farre as to bid defiance to the face of God. There is one that writes to this purpoſe,<note place="margin">Specul. magnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exemplorum, Exemp. 103. diſt. 5. Hondorf. Theatr. Hiſt. p. 114.</note> (the Author unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, is ſaid to live about 170 years ſince) <hi>That three men were found in</hi> Lovaine, <hi>a City in</hi> Brabant, <hi>playing at Tables in a Cellar on Good Friday at night; and withall, ſwearing and blaſpheming terribly: A CitiZen paſsing along the ſtreet where this Cellar was, and finding certaine men of that ſtreet lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting over a ſtranger ſeeming to be miſerably wounded and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmeared with bloud, the Citizen demanded of the ſtanders there, who it was that hurt the man;</hi> the anſwer was made, <hi>Thoſe Table-players in the Cellar. The Citizen thereupon haſtens to thoſe Gameſters, acquaints them what they were charged withall, being very angry that they would ſo much forget them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at that time: they all deny with one accord the ſight of any ſuch man, and the ſtriking or hurting of any: and forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with left off their ſwearing and gaming, and away together they went with the Citizen to finde out this ſuppoſed wounded man; who being diligently ſought after, and not found, they concluded (ſo inſtructed) that they had wounded</hi> Chriſtum dominum, contumeliis affectum, <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s <hi>Lord, by their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachful contempts &amp; obloquies.</hi> Of another the ſame Author reports, That being at Tables, and having loſt all his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:165729:12"/>in a ſwearing rage (too too frequent with common Gameſters) finding a Bow and an Arrow, he ſhot the ſame Arrow as far as he could (in revenge againſt the Almighty) up into the Aire, which returned unto him again all Bloud. Now whether theſe relations be ſtories, or fables, truthes, or tales, I have not to ſay, but ſure I am, that a good uſe may be made of them by any one that is willing to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed and inſtructed. Somewhat more I ſhall produce tending to this purpoſe, that comes neer (I ſuppoſe home) both to Story and Truth. In the year 1553 in <hi>Helvetia,</hi> (now <hi>ZwitZerland</hi>) neer the City <hi>Williſaw,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theatr. Hiſt. pag. 115.</note> diſtant three miles from <hi>Lucerna</hi> it thus happened. Three Dicers having gotten a paire of Tables into the field cloſe by the City walls, they fell to play, and in their gaming, one of the Gameſters, whoſe name was <hi>Ulrichus Schrolerus,</hi> having loſt much money, began exceedingly to curſe and ſwear. The Dice, for the preſent, turned their courſe with better ſucceſſe to the Swearer; he goes on, plays, and ſwears as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and at length breaks out (ſee how buſie the Devill is, how active upon all opportunities offered to do miſchiefe, how deſpightfull againſt the Majeſty of God) in theſe termes with a Dagger in his hand. <hi>Si modò fortuna me fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fellerit, arreptum pugionem in ipſius Dei corpus quouſque po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tero interquebo: If now againe fortune deceive me, I will ſheath this Dagger,</hi> (catcht up) <hi>as far as I am able into the Body of God.</hi> But fortune never conſtant, fell off again, whereat this Monſter being againe diſpleaſed, forthwith drew this Dagger, and taking it by the point, up he throws it towards Heaven as far as he could: The Dagger vaniſhed in the Aire, and five drops of Bloud fell upon the Table. Out of hand the Devill ſeizeth, and away body and ſoul he carries <hi>Ulrichus,</hi> with ſuch violence and noiſe, that a fear and tumult was ſtirred up throughout the whole City. The
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:165729:12"/>other two remaining in the place, endeavoured what they could to rub out the Bloud, but all in vaine, for the more they laboured, the more the nitor, or ruddy brightneſſe of the bloud appeared. Whilſt they thus laboured, many perſons came out of the City and found them at it, whom preſently they apprehended and took into the City with them: And as they were leading through the gate of the City, the one of them fell down, from, and out of whoſe body Wormes, and Lice, in ſuch abundance came forth, that the very Carkaſe was left without skin, and ſo ended his unhappy life in this moſt miſerable and fearfull man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: Which being ſeen, without delay, the third Malefactor was preſently dragg'd away to execution, and put to death, as his crime ſo highly ſinfull and horrid well deſerved. Now if any man ſhall queſlion the truth of this relation, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor is <hi>Andreas Hendorffius, Coeleſtis doctrinae praeco &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propugnator ſtrenuus,</hi> ſo ſtiled by the Tranſlator of that work of his entituled <hi>Theatrum Hiſtoricum,</hi> from whence I had this Story written firſt in Dutch, and afterwards tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated into Latine by <hi>Philippus Lonicerus,</hi> a very learned Proteſtant. Which Author <hi>(Hendorffius)</hi> makes mention in his foreſaid Book of the former of the two foregoing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations. It is a grief to me to ſay, but 'tis true that I ſay, many and many of theſe examples I could rehearſe, but I paſſe them over: For as <hi>Dives</hi> tormented in Hell, prayed <hi>Abraham that one might be ſent to his Fathers houſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 16.</note> 
               <hi>to teſtifie to his brethren, leſt they alſo ſhould come into that place of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. They have</hi> (ſaith <hi>Abraham</hi>) <hi>Moſes, and the Prophets, if they will not hear them, neither will they be perſwaded, though one roſe from the dead:</hi> So may I ſay, that if what hath been ſaid be not ſufficient to affright and terrifie the ſoul of the Swearer, the addition of more will be needleſſe: Yet on a little further, with Gods bleſſing and aſſiſtance, I
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:165729:13"/>ſhall adventure to goe. God gives charge to forbear the profanation of his name, by vaine and unneceſſary Oathes, which he hath done in his Word with threats and meanaces of puniſhment upon the profaners;<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.11.</note> And <hi>becauſe</hi> (as the Wiſe man ſaith) <hi>ſentence againſt an evill work is not execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſpeedily, therefore the heart of the ſonnes of men is fully ſet in them to doe evill.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.24.</note> But as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>That ſome mens ſins are open beforehand, going before to judgement, and ſome mens they follow after:</hi> So truly ſhall we finde, that God takes ſome few (one perhaps of ten thouſands) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the very act (as I may ſay) of wickedneſſe, and ſuppoſe this one thus puniſhed, as an example to thoſe many as high malefactors, not that his puniſhment (ſuppoſe by ſome dreadfull death) ſhall any whit at all allay the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of his indignation, or mitigate, blunt, or dull the ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Divine Wrath towards others, but rather it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a cauſe of extenſion, and aggravation of wrath, that will <hi>plague,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 50.2. Hoſ. 5.14.</note> will <hi>tear,</hi> will <hi>rage</hi> to all eternity, without hope of reconciliation, againſt ſuch a one as nothwithſtanding ſuch menaces, ſuch monitions, ſuch examples will ſtill pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to goe on,<note place="margin">Pſal. 68.21.</note> and doe evill impenitently, he will <hi>wound</hi> (as the Pſalmiſt ſaith) <hi>the hairy ſcalp of ſuch a one as goeth on ſtill in his tranſgreſsion.</hi> Oh what ſhould I ſay? To tell an inveterate Swearer, that <hi>becauſe of ſwearing, the Land mourneth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 23.10. Zee. 5.3, 4.</note> hee'l not believe it, though the Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> affirme it, however hee'l not leave it, though <hi>Zecharies</hi> flying roll be out againſt him, threatning the deſtruction of him, and the conſumption of his houſe. Surely he cares not for flying rolls, nor what's within them, and without them; nor who, nor what mournes, if he may ſwear, and be merry, he takes no further thought. Threaten ſuch a one with Gods Judgments, he is inſenſible, he knowes not (having liv'd ſo long untouch'd) hardly believes the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>douted
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:165729:13"/>approaches of Divine Vengeance, that will fall upon him ſooner or later, he cannot eſcape: <hi>Job</hi> ſaith he ſhall not, <hi>the wicked ſhall not eſcape,</hi> ſaith he,<note place="margin">Job 11.20. Prov. 19.5.</note> nor <hi>he that tells lies,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon.</hi> What then ſhall we doe with ſuch perſons? <hi>NebuchadneZZar</hi> made a decree, <hi>That who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſpake any thing amiſſe againſt the God of</hi> Shadrach,<note place="margin">Dan. 3.29. Levit. 24.11.</note> Meſhach, <hi>and</hi> Abednego, <hi>ſhould be cut in pieces. Blaſphemy</hi> was puniſhed with death in the time of the law. But the courſe that <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> preſcribeth to the people of <hi>Antioch</hi> where he preached, againſt the ſwearers of that place was this. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſt. hom. ad populum Antioch.</note> 
               <hi>If</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>thou hear any one in the ſtreet, or in the midſt of the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket blaſpeming God: Goe unto him, and rebuke him for it, and if ſtroaks be needfull, refuſe not to beſtow them, rap him on the face, daſh him on the mouth, ſanctifie thy hand by thy ſtroak. And if any accuſe thee, and draw thee to the Court, or Tribunall of Juſtice, follow them, and if the Judge require an accompt or reaſon of what thou didst, tell him boldly, that he hath blaſphemed the King of Angels, &amp;c.</hi> This was <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes</hi> advice, which I propoſe not to imitation, but much approve and commend his Chriſtian zeale and pious ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſity to ſtand up in the defence of Gods honour, ſo much then, and I am afraid much more now contemned and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lactantius</hi> tells us, that at <hi>Lindum,</hi> which is a towne of <hi>Rhodes,</hi> there are Sacrifices done to <hi>Hercules,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lanct. l. 1. c. 21. p. 86.</note> the manner and cuſtome whereof is much different from others, for they are not celebrated <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as (ſaith he) the Greeks call it, by good langage, or well ſpeaking, but by evill ſpeaking and curſing. And they account ſuch Sacrifices to goe for nought, if at any time there chanceth to fall from any mans mouth there preſent a good word, though unawares.</p>
            <p>Here's mad Service, fit for none but the Devil. O let none
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:165729:14"/>of our Sacrifices (none I ſay of ours that carry about us, or ſhould ſo doe, Temples for the holy Ghoſt to reſide and abide in) be ever ſtained with ſuch pollutions. For as the Rabbins ſay, <hi>The Prayer of a Drinker,</hi> (that is, a laviſh drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, or drunkard) <hi>is an abomination:</hi> How much more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable is the prayer of a laviſh ſweares, whoſe ſins, (as I may truly ſay) without a cauſe; nature being far leſſe prone, if prone at all, to this then to the other, there being a naturall deſire, and appetite after bodily ſuſtentation, which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times falls out to be exceſſive; but as touching Swearing, what cauſe for that? I have now done in a word. The Prophet <hi>Hoſea</hi> denounceth Gods judgements againſt the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> He tells them that the Lord had a controverſie with the inhabitants of the Land, becauſe there was no truth, nor mercy, nor knowledge of God in the Land. <hi>By ſwearing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 4.2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>and lying, and killing, and ſtealing, and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting adultery, they break out, and bloud toucheth bloud. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>ſhall the land mourn, and every one that dwelleth therein ſhall languiſh with the beaſts of the field, and with the fouls of heaven, yea, the fiſhes of the Sea alſo ſhall be taken away.</hi> God deliver <hi>England</hi> from this Judgment. To conclude, let us hearken to the counſell of the ſon of <hi>Sirach:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ecclus. 23.7, 8, 9, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Hear O ye children the diſcipline of the mouth: He that keepeth it, ſhall never be taken in his lips. The ſinner ſhall be left in his fooliſhneſſe, both the evill ſpeaker, and the proud, ſhall fall thereby. Accuſtome not thy mouth to ſwearing, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther uſe thy ſelfe to the</hi> [<note n="*" place="margin">Claud. Bad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſus. Janſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius.</note> raſh and irreverent] <hi>naming of the Holy one. For as a ſervant that is continually beaten ſhall not be without a blew mark, ſo he that ſweareth, and nameth God continually, ſhall not be faultleſſe. A man that uſeth much ſwearing ſhall be filled with iniquity, and the plague ſhall never depart from his houſe. If he ſhall offend, his ſin ſhall be upon him; and if he acknowledge not his ſinne, he maketh a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:165729:14"/>double offence; if he ſwear in vaine, and he ſhall not be innocent, but his houſe ſhall be full of calamities. There is a</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Melius eſt ſimpliciter &amp; ſimplicibus &amp; nudis verbis rem dicere qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> religioſa affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matione con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmare. Mihi haec tranſlatio verbi <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in textu, videtur impium ſceleratumque prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>textum nominis Dei ad orationem fraudulentam &amp; mendacem accommodatum ſignificare. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duell. minot. in Locum.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Word that is clothed about with death, God grant that it be not found in the heritage of</hi> Jacob, <hi>for all ſuch things ſhall be found farre from the godly, and they ſhall not wallow in their ſins. Uſe not thy mouth to intemperate ſwearing, for therein is the word of ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God give a bleſſing to what is here endeavoured: Let him only have the glory to whom it is onely due, and his poor ſervant acceptance before him, in, and through Jeſus Chriſt, to whom with the Father, and the Holy Ghoſt, be aſcribed all praiſe, all power, all dominion, with all hearty thankſgiving from every Congregation, Church and Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, both now, and for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
